"Do the Health Impacts of Ultra-Processed Foods
Apply to Plant-Based Meats?"
In two Harvard cohorts,
researchers followed
about a hundred thousand men
and women for decades,
and found that high consumption
of ultra-processed foods
is associated
with dying earlier,
which provides support
for limiting consumption
of certain types
of ultra-processed foods
for long term health.
In particular, processed
meat, poultry, seafood,
which generally showed
the strongest
and most consistent associations
with mortality.
So here, the negative,
life-shortening effects
of ultra-processed foods
was really mostly
talking about the negative,
life-shortening effects
of processed meats like burgers,
chicken nuggets,
and fish sticks.
But the association between
more ultra-processed foods
and higher mortality
appears to be present
even among vegetarians.
Yes, plant-based diets,
which reduce or avoid eggs,
dairy, fish, and other meats,
have been linked
to a reduced risk
of various chronic diseases,
including our leading killer,
cardiovascular disease.
But that doesn’t mean you can
live off vegan doughnuts.
Non-ultra-processed plant foods
like fruits and vegetables
are associated with lower risk
of disease,
but ultra-processed foods
like Oreos and Mountain Dew
are associated
with higher risks.
So, dietary guidelines
shouldn’t just tell people
to cut down on meat
and other animal-sourced foods,
but also to cut down on junk.
No big surprise,
but this is how
the paper was reported on:
"The hidden health hazards
of vegan sausages."
"Vegan fake meats are linked
to increase in heart deaths."
What? If you look at the study,
meat alternatives only made up
0.2% of their diet.
39.4% of their diet
was composed
of ultra-processed plant foods,
but only about one 500th
of their intake
was meat alternatives.
The study participants were
eating 30 times more pastries.
Aren’t those
more likely to be the culprit
in the relationship
between ultra-processed foods
and disease?
14 times more French fries
and candy.
Even 4 times more vodka
and other hard liquor.
But apparently, there’s not
a lot of click-bait to be had
telling people not to eat
vodka and cream puffs.
If you really wanted to see
if meat alternatives
were an issue,
you’d have to run
more granular studies
that separate out
meat alternatives for analysis.
This study on obesity
had an eclectic category
of ultra-processed
"fruits and vegetables"
that included meat alternatives
along with powdered soup
and fruit compote,
and there was no tie to obesity.
The culprits were mostly soda,
ice cream, mayonnaise,
baloney, fish sticks,
and the like.
But ideally, we’d have
a study big enough
to completely separate out
plant-based meat.
If only there were some
epic study.
And indeed, here it is,
the EPIC study.
More than a quarter million
people were followed
for more than a decade.
Yes, higher consumption
of ultra-processed foods
increases the risk of cancer
and cardiometabolic
multimorbidity,
like cardiovascular disease
and diabetes.
Yes, but which
ultra-processed foods?
It’s the animal-based
ultra-processed foods
like processed meat
and soda.
No associated risk
with ultra-processed breads
and cereals or plant-based meat.
And when it comes to diabetes,
plant-based meats and milks
appeared to cut the risk
of developing diabetes in half.
Animal-based products
were associated
with more than twice the risk.
Plant-based alternatives
were associated
with less than half.
The authors concluded
that higher consumption
of ultra-processed foods
may increase
the risk of cancer
and other diseases,
but their data really only show
that the consumption of foods
of animal origin and soft drinks
is associated with such a risk,
which is like, duh.
Indeed, if you go back
and exclude
the animal-based foods
and sodas,
the relationship between
ultra-processed foods
and these multiple diseases
disappears.
So, the only
ultra-processed food
that appears
to be killing people is meat.
In that case,
instead of being a contributor,
plant-based meats
may be the solution
to the ultra-processed foods
problem.
The only other
ultra-processed study
that separated out
plant-based meats
looked at telomere length,
which is used
to measure cellular aging.
Their study found
that a higher consumption
of total ultra-processed foods
was associated
with a shorter telomere length,
which is a sign
of accelerated aging.
However, some subclasses
may be associated
with longer telomere length,
suggesting slower aging.
And the class
of foods associated
with the longest telomeres?
Vegetarian alternatives,
plant-based meat.
There have been
other population studies
on plant-based meats.
This one found
that those who ate
plant-based meat daily
appeared to cut their risk
of hip fracture in half
compared to those eating
it less than once a week.
Schoolchildren who eat
plant-based meats
appear to have half the odds
of being overweight
compared to those
eating regular meat.
And girls who eat more meat
start their periods
at an earlier age,
which may help explain
why childhood meat consumption
is linked to breast cancer
later in life,
since the earlier
you start your period,
the higher your lifetime risk.
In contrast,
those eating plant-based meats
appear able to delay
the onset of menstruation
by nine months.
But observational studies
like these
can’t ever prove
cause-and-effect.
For that, you need
interventional trials.
There have been 10
published up through 2023
and a few more since then.
I did a video on the Stanford
SWAP-MEAT study
that showed swapping out
a few servings a day of meat
for plant-based
meat alternatives
for two months significantly
decreased circulating levels
of the microbiome toxin TMAO,
as well as lowered
LDL cholesterol and body weight.
But there have been about
a dozen other studies,
including this four-year long
randomized clinical trial
in which people with diabetes
and ailing kidneys
were randomized to replace
half their animal protein intake
with an ultra-processed
plant-based meat replacement
called TVP.
The researchers saw
significant improvements
in blood sugar control,
cholesterol,
triglycerides, inflammation,
and significant improvements
in their kidney function.
I’ll cover all these studies.
Stay tuned.
And, if you don't want to wait,
I've got a new book out
that covers them all,
a short peer-reviewed paper that's
free to download at see.nf/ultra,
and a CME-approved webinar
you can watch as well.